in this video we're going to talk about
how to solve problems
associated with rotational kinematics
so let me give you a list of formulas
that you need to know
so on the left side
we're going to put all of the linear
equations that is associated with
translational motion
and on the right side
all of the angular equations
that's associated with rotational motion
so the first equation that you need to
know is if an object is moving with
constant speed
that is if it has zero acceleration
so d is equal to v t
d can be used as displacement or
distance distance and displacement is
the same if an object moves in a
straight line without changing direction
angular displacement is equal to omega
times t
notice the similarities between these
two equations
so v
represents linear speed or linear
velocity omega is angular speed or
angular velocity
d
can represent displacement or distance
depending on how it's used
theta can be angular distance or angular
displacement
now what about if an object is moving
with a constant acceleration value
so then we have these equations
v final
is equal to v initial plus a t
where v final could represent the final
speed or final velocity
in the angular universe it's going to be
omega final is equal to omega initial
plus alpha t
so whenever you see an a replace with an
alpha
now the next equation that you need to
know is this one
v final squared is equal to v initial
squared
plus 2ad
and the angular version of that equation
is omega final squared is equal to omega
initial squared
plus 2 alpha
times theta
so anytime you see a d replace it with
theta
if you see a v
replace it with omega
and if you see an a
replace it with alpha
now the third equation that you need to
know
is this one d
is equal to v initial t
plus
one half a t squared
and on the other side it's going to be
omega i mean not omega but theta is
equal to
omega initial times t
plus
one half
alpha t squared
and there's one more equation the
displacement is equal to the average
speed
or average velocity
which is
the sum of the initial and the final
velocity divided by two times t
so this is a variant of this equation
instead of using v using average v
so omega is one half
i mean theta is one half omega initial
plus omega final times t
so you may want to write down these
equations
for the problems that are about to come
shortly
now there are some other equations that
we'll need to add to the list
the first one is this one
linear displacement is equal to the
angular displacement times the radius
now perhaps you've seen this equation in
trig as arc length is equal to the angle
in radians times the radius it's very
similar
now the next one linear velocity is
equal to angular velocity times the
radius
and linear acceleration is equal to the
angular acceleration times the radius
notice how similar these three equations
are
so make sure
to add
these three equations to your list
now let's start with this problem
a wheel spins at a constant angular
speed of 24 radians per second how many
revolutions will the disc go through in
5 minutes
so we don't have any acceleration in
this problem
so the main equation that we need is
theta
i'm not sure what happened there but
theta is equal to omega times t
now we have omega which is 24 radians
per second
and we have the time in minutes but we
need to convert it to seconds
one minute is equal to 60 seconds
so 5 minutes is going to be 5 times 60
which is 300 seconds
which i'm going to put right here
so if we multiply omega in radians per
second by the time in seconds
this will give us
the angular distance in radians so it's
24 times 300 which is seven thousand two
hundred radians
now we need to convert this angle to
revolutions
so what you need to know is that
one revolution
is equal to 2 pi radians
2 pi radians is 360 degrees and that
represents a full circle
so take 7 200 and divided by 2 pi or
6.28
and you should get 1146
revolutions
so the will is going to make 11 46
complete cycles or complete revolutions
during the five minutes
now let's move on to part b
how far
along the ground will the will travel at
this rate in five minutes
so here's the will here's the ground
we want to know
what is the linear distance
as opposed to
the angular distance
so how can we get this answer
so recall that arc length or linear
distance is equal to omega i mean theta
times r
but we need to use the angle in radians
not revolutions
so it's going to be 7200 radians
multiplied by the radius
which is uh
i didn't give you the radius of the
wheel
so that's the one thing i forgot to do
in this problem
so let's say the radius of the wheel is
two meters
so that means that
one radian will have an arc length of
two meters
so the distance that the wheel will
travel is 7200 times two
so that's going to be 14 000
and 400 meters
so that's the answer to part b
if the radius of the wheel is two meters
now let's move on to number two
a disc
speeds up from rest
at a constant rate of 2.5 radians per
second square
what is the final angular speed of the
disk after 18 seconds
well let's write down what we know
so we know the initial angular speed is
zero because it starts from rest
our goal is to calculate the final
angular speed
we're given the angular acceleration
it's 2.5 radians per second squared
and we know the time is 18 seconds
so what equation
contains
these four variables
so the equation that we need is this one
omega final is equal to omega initial
plus alpha t
omega initial is zero
alpha is 2.5
radians per second squared
and the time
is 18 seconds
so this will give us the final angular
speed in radians per second
so it's 2.5
times 18
which is 45 radians per second
so that's it for part a
now what about part b
how many revolutions
will the disc go through during this
time period
so what equation
can help us to calculate
the angle theta
theta
is equal to omega initial times t plus
one half
alpha t squared
so omega initial is zero
alpha is 2.5
and t is 18.
so theta is 405 radians
now we need to convert this to
revolutions
so one revolution
as we know it's two pi
radians
so let's take 405 and divide it by 2pi
so you should get 64.46
revolutions
so that's the angular distance
that the disc travels during this time
period
now what about part c
what is the linear speed of a point
at the edge of the disk after 18 seconds
keep in mind the final angular speed
we said was 45 radians per second it was
18 times 2.5 and that's how we got that
answer
so to find the final linear speed
from the final angular speed it's just
omega times r so we just got to multiply
these two values and we have the radius
of the disk
it's 50 centimeters
which is equivalent to 0.5 meters
so keep in mind 100 centimeters is equal
to 1 meter so you got to divide 50 by
100 to get 0.5 meters
so the linear speed after 18 seconds is
going to be basically the final speed at
that time
so it's omega which is 45 radians per
second
multiplied by the radius
which is 0.5 meters
per radian
so when the angle is 1 radian the arc
length is 0.5 meters
so 45 times 0.5
is 22.5
so we have a final angular speed i mean
not angular speed but final linear speed
of 22.5
meters per second in this problem so
that's the answer to part c
number three
a disc with a diameter of 60 centimeters
speeds up from 20 radians per second to
40 radians per second in five seconds
how many revolutions will the disc go
through during that time period
so how can we find the answer for this
problem
let's make a list of what we know
the initial speed is 20
the final angular speed
is 40
t is 5
and we have the radius which is one half
of the diameter so the radius is 30
centimeters which is 0.3 meters
so when you're asked to find the
revolutions you need to find theta first
which is going to be in radians and then
convert it to revolutions
so what equation should we use
in order to calculate
theta
i'm going to use this one
it's the average
angular speed multiplied by the time
and the average angular speed is
basically the sum of the initial and the
final angular speed divided by two
so it's one half
omega initial plus omega final
times t
so the initial angular speed is 20 the
final angular speed is 40 and the time
difference is 5.
so if you add 20 plus 40 and divide by 2
this will give you an average
angular speed of 30 radians per second
so we're going to multiply that by 5
seconds
and so the unit seconds will cancel 30
times 5 is 150.
so the angular distance is 150
radians
now let's convert it to revolutions
so let's take 150 radians
and convert its revolutions
so 2 pi radians
is equal to 1 revolution
so 150 divided by 2 pi
is 23.87
revolutions
so that's the answer to part a
now let's move on to part b
what is the average angular acceleration
of the disk
so what do we need in order to find it
it turns out that we already have
everything that we need
so we can use this equation omega final
is equal to omega initial plus
alpha t
so if you solve for alpha you got to
move this to this side and then divide
by t
the average angular acceleration is
going to be
omega final minus omega initial divided
by t
so it's the final angular speed of 40
minus the initial angular speed of 20
divided by 5 seconds
so the change in angular speed is 20.
so 20 over 5 will give us the average
acceleration which is 4
radians per second squared
so that's the answer to part b
now part c
what is the average linear acceleration
of the disk
the linear acceleration
is the angular acceleration times r
so it's going to be 4 radians per second
squared times the radius
of 0.3 meters
so 4 times 0.3
that's 1.2
so the average linear acceleration
is 1.2 meters per second squared
and so that's it for this problem
now let's work on the last problem of
this video
a wheel with a diameter of 80
centimeters speeds up from 30 radians
per second to 80 radians per second
the linear acceleration of the edge of
the wheel is 15 meters per second
squared how many revolutions will the
wheel go through during this period
so all we gotta find is theta in this
problem
and we know the radius is half of the
diameter so it's 40 centimeters and if
we divide that by 100 that's 0.4 meters
the initial angular speed is 30
the final angular speed is 80.
and we're given the linear acceleration
which is 15 meters per second squared
well if we have the linear acceleration
we could find the angular acceleration
so the angle acceleration is the linear
acceleration divided by r
so that's 15
divided by 0.4
and so the angle acceleration is
37.5 radians per second squared
so now we can calculate
theta
so the equation that i'm going to use
is this one
omega final squared is equal to omega
initial squared
plus
alpha
theta
so solving for theta i've got to move
this to this side where it's going to
become negative and then divide both
sides by 2 alpha
so theta is going to be omega final
squared
minus omega initial squared divided by 2
alpha
so the final speed is 80 the initial
speed is 30
and alpha
is 37.5
so 80 squared is 6400
30 squared is 900
and 2 times 37.5
is 75.
6400 minus 900
is 5500 if we divide that by 75
this is going to be
73.33 radians
now we need to convert it to revolutions
so we need to divide it by 2 pi radians
that's a terrible looking two
so this will
is going to go through an angular
distance of
11.67
revolutions
and so this is the answer
you